With AI agents on cloud code, co-work
and codeex becoming more powerful by the
day. Building good skills will be one of
the most important things to get good at
in 2026. Building agent skills allows
anyone to automate any workflow by
simply prompting it and can even become
self-improving. And good skills will
likely become monetizable soon. So, in
this video, I'll show you why you need
to learn skill engineering, show you
what skills actually are and when to use
them, and a simple framework to build
better skills than 99% of people. Now
this guide should help you whether you
work with cloud code, co-work, openai,
google as they all have integrated uh
skills by now. Now before we dive into
what skills are and how to build them
effectively, let me quickly explain why
learning skills is a big deal. Now we're
all seeing that these AI agents are
getting really powerful. But no matter
how good they get, they still need that
specific those specific guard rails,
context and SOPs around all the unique
ways you and a business do things and
use software. Now we've tried to solve
this before. Of course, we have projects
and custom GPTs where you set a system
prompt and add context files. But
generally, the problem with these is
they're isolated. You're hopping between
different windows. They don't really
self-improve and can't handle a lot of
context. On the other side, of course,
we have NAND and automation platforms
that hardcode the guardrails and make
the system deterministic. And for fully
deterministic non-human in the loop
workflows, these are still great. But
most day-to-day work isn't actually
deterministic. Uh the processes aren't
always clear-cut. Uh it's context
dependent. It requires judgment. And
that's why human in the loop is often
really important to get good outputs
from AI. And skills sit in the middle.
They're essentially instructions for an
AI agent on how to do a specific
process. They can self-improve. They
have human in the loop. But unlike a
project or custom GPT, thousands of
skills can be accessed by the same
agent. And the game changer is that they
can be created and updated by simply
prompting. And that means anyone can
start automating their tasks and
workflows through a single interface on
cloud code, co-work. They're also
sharable across your business. So one
person's process and domain expertise
can instantly be used by the entire team
which of course has huge implications
for onboarding consistency and how a
company operates and if thousands of
these specific capabilities can be given
to one very capable general agent it
seems likely uh that AI agents will
slowly become the single interface for
doing work. Now, of course, we are very
early with this, but I predict that
building the skill infrastructure for
these agents to do specific tasks well
will not only allow you and your company
to become far more productive, it will
also become monetizable. Sort of like a
new software layer. But just like with
software engineering, prompt
engineering, and AI automation
engineering, you need to actually get
good at it. Even though anyone can
create skills through prompts, the same
skill can produce completely different
outputs depending on how you build them.
For example, this is an infographic that
I got out of an infographic skill that I
quickly created. And this is the output
of the same input of an infographic
skill I put a lot more effort in. As you
can see, it's a lot clearer and a lot
more aligned to my brand. I'll show you
a full demo of the infographic scale
later in this video. Also, if you want
access to that infographic scale and all
of the other skills me and my team are
building out, you can also check out my
AI accelerator where we uh list them all
for you to download or customize. Now,
before showing you how to build these
types of skills, it's good to understand
what skills actually are. And simply
put, agent skills are folders of
instructions, scripts, and resources
that agents can use to do things more
accurately and efficiently. And at the
core, we have the skill.md file. You can
basically see this as an instruction on
how to do a process. Think of it like a
system prompt, a cloud project, or a
custom GPT. But besides that process
instruction, we can have additional
instructions on how and when to use
knowledge files, how and when to use
tools, how and when to spin up sub aents
and how and when to use code executions.
So the skill MD you can basically see as
the SOP. Now that skill MD is just the
core. What makes skills more powerful
are those additional reference files or
the context we add. Now what kind of
reference files can we have? Now
firstly, we can build really simple
skills with no reference files at all.
It's just a skill MD or a process
instruction. For example, we have an
sales account research skill here from
Enthropic which has no additional
reference files, just the skill MD here.
And the skill MD, as you can see,
includes an execution flow, right? Step
one, parse request, step two, web
search, right? Step three, enrichment,
and step four CRM check. But commonly
when we build our skills, we want to add
some reference files to provide the
skill with more information. Firstly, we
can have text files. For example, common
ones you might want to include are
example outputs, style guides, context
around your ICP, uh your background,
etc. For example, in my newsletter
writer skill, you can see I have
multiple reference files here to give
the skill more context on my background,
what we do, my ICP and voice
personality. Another common one to use
is an MCP instructions file, which
basically lays out to the agent how to
use a specific tool efficiently in this
specific skill process. for example, the
way you navigate or use your CRM for
this specific task. Now, don't worry.
Your agent can build these MCP
documents. Now, a second type of
reference file we can have in there are
assets or non-ext files like images,
presentations, videos, or even uh
binary, for example, to give it good
output examples of a presentation layout
that you want. And then lastly,
reference files can even include code
scripts, Python or JS functions that can
take actions like doing API calls in a
software or executing functions. For
example, my infographic scale, we have a
script to do an API call to the nano
banana Google API call. So you can see
that these skills can be very simple or
can become quite complex and can look a
lot more like a software except skills
of course are software for AI agents.
But how are we able to give one AI agent
access to thousands of these skills,
feed it all of these documents without
overloading it with context? Now this is
done through a process called
progressive disclosure. Now it sounds
complicated, but it's not. Basically,
when we create or upload a new skill and
give it to our AI agent in cloud co-work
or code, only the metadata, which is the
description and the name are stored in
the agent memory. In my infographic
skill, this is the name and this is the
description. And this is how your agent
knows when to trigger or use a specific
skill. And then only when the skill is
triggered, the skill MD or the process
will be loaded into the context window
of the agent to understand how to
execute on this specific process. And
only when the skill instructs to use a
reference file, it loads the reference
file into the context window. And
because of this progressive disclosure
of context, we can give one agent access
to thousands of potential skills. Now, I
see a lot of confusion between plugins
and skills too. So, let me explain it
very quickly. Plugins are essentially
packaged or bundled sets of skills,
commands, agents, and connectors. And
this basically means and does three
things. First, it adds a layer of
complexity on top of skills because
plugins can include multiple skills. It
can include commands which serve as
workflow triggers that can trigger
multiple skills in sequence to automate
more complex tasks. It can have
specialized agent teams and a preset set
of connectors. So, we can add a lot more
functionality to these plugins. Second,
through plugins, these bundled packages
can easily be shared and divided between
company departments. Sales teams can get
a sales plugin. Marketing teams can get
a marketing plugin each with the
connectors and skills that each
department needs. And thirdly, these
plugins are also becoming uh versionable
uh skills too by the way, which means
they can be updated at any time across
any account that uses them. And because
of these characteristics, plugins start
to look a lot more like software of
course or SAS. And I predict that SAS
will start to launch their own plugins
with their specific functionalities.
Now, if you want to learn more about
plugins, I recently did a video on it.
So, I'll make sure to link it in the
description below, too. But skills are
really the key aspect even inside of
these plugins. And even though we have
plugins, we can still directly build,
trigger, and access skills even without
these plugins. Now, skills and plugins
are relevant for any industry, business,
department, and any niche workflow. And
we're seeing three layers of skills and
plugins appear. uh we have the general
plugins and skills uh for example the
ones built by Entropic or OpenAI um but
we're already seeing marketplaces of
skills like Skills MP Smithy um where
people are building and potentially
selling them and potentially SAS
businesses will start creating their own
plugins now as these will have to be
general purpose skills in order to be
relevant to multiple industries and
businesses companies will want to build
their own ones based on their unique
processes or customize some of these
general skills but even within a company
it makes sense for different employees
and different people to customize skills
to their specific way of working and
their specific workflows. For example,
an entropic or third party, let's say
sales outreach skill can be useful, but
a company probably wants to customize
and improve it by adding uh the company
brand tone, the ICP and the business
context. And one uh sales rep's
copywriting style will be different than
anothers. So, they can even start
customizing uh those skills for their
specific copyrightiting style. for
example. Of course, if you as an
individual start to get good at it and
you have specific domain expertise and
build a skill out of it, you can
potentially monetize it by providing it
to the general public. So, how do we
actually build these skills ourselves?
Now, we can first of all customize
entropics or the third party provider
skills. There are multiple of these
marketplaces now, but the real unlock is
really building them yourself because
every person and every company has their
specific ways of working and their
specific expertise. Now, there are two
main ways to build your own. First way
is you do a task once manually with an
AI agent and then ask it to save it as a
skill. And the second way is to instruct
it on how to build the skill right away.
For example, here I downloaded a third
party provider meta ad scale from one of
the marketplaces, imported it and used
it here in my own account. And then I
asked it to use this skill combined with
my specific knowledge sources to create
a new skill that helps me create ads.
And then it created a new skill which I
can add to my library. Customizing
Entropics built-in plugins and skills is
also very easy. You can just go to
skills, click on edit and customize with
claude or even the plugins by just
clicking here on customize. And here I
created my own skill by just prompting
it and giving it some reference files.
Now whatever the method, applying some
best practices is important. So let me
start by saying that building good
skills is kind of like an art. It's the
art of putting your domain expertise of
a process into something productizable
and usable for an agent. The more I do
this, the more similarities I see
between skill engineering and software
engineering, but it's sort of like
software engineering for an AI agent. uh
but you have to think about UX right
when to add in human in the loop you
have to think about context engineering
right which balance of context uh
produces the best outcomes you're adding
features removing things handling edge
cases etc the beautiful thing with
skills is you can easily update them
with prompt so skills are never finished
and what I've learned is the more you
use them the better they get I've
probably updated and iterated on my
infographic skill around five times to
get to the outcome that I get now now
the first step is the step that most
people skip but what makes the biggest
impact uh before prompting to build or
customize a scale, you really do want to
take a step back and think about the
ideal step-by-step process to get to a
good outcome. You want to think about uh
what knowledge sources or additional
information you can give your AI agent
in this skill to do a better job. Now,
generally, some context or reference
files that I recommend you have,
especially if you're going to use these
skills more for marketing or sales
related uh skills, is what we do.
basically a description of your business
or description of your ICP of your voice
personality if you're using this for uh
LinkedIn etc. newsletter strategy in
this case I have this also for my
YouTube for my LinkedIn etc and also
writing framework these are some of the
documents that I reuse across different
skills too so I highly recommend this
now if you don't have these reference
files yet you can do it together with
cloud for example here I asked it I want
to create a YouTube strategy document
that I can later give when I'm building
skills for research ideation scripting
etc and then I basically ask it to ask
me some questions about my YouTube
strategy and through the planning mode
as you can see here ask questions etc
you'll get more and more context text
and at the end here you can see club
generated a YouTube strategy document
for me which I can then reuse in
multiple uh YouTube skills that I create
and once you have a few of these
building skills will get a lot more
efficient. Now once you have that of
course you want to think about which
tools or software the agent needs in
order to uh do this task and then if
possible you always want to prepare good
output examples and this is generally
the thing that impacts performance the
most. Now once you have that sort of
clear we move to the building which of
course in this case is prompting. Now I
just go through a framework that I like
to use which is not hard science but I
think can help you uh to think about
what to include to get to a good first
outcome uh of your skill. Now first you
want to define the name of the skill and
how the skill should be triggered. So in
this case the name of the skill should
be infographic generator and should be
triggered anytime a user mentions he
wants to generate or create an
infographic. And this is what the agent
uses to write the meta description. Then
just like with prompting you want to
define the goal or objective for the
skill. Uh it can be quite short because
we dive a lot deeper into the process
later. Now, in this case, an infographic
skill that creates quality infographics
according to my brand style for LinkedIn
and newsletters. Then, we want to give
Claude context on connectors, APIs or
MCPS that it needs uh to use in this
scale. Now, if there's a specific table,
maybe a page or a process it should take
in that software for this uh skill, you
can also describe that here. And then
you want to lay out the process uh step
by step. This is one of the most
important things and it's good to
actually spend some time on it. Now a
good way to think about what to include
in each step is what does it need to do?
First of all, when do you want a human
in the loop? What kind of human in the
loop do you want? With the dynamic QA
boxes of cloud, we can now choose
between check boxes, open field, single
select, etc. Which kind of becomes like
UX design. And for what additional
context should be used to do this task
better? If it's very short, you can add
it in the prompt. But if you have a
specific file it needs to read, you want
to specify that for each of the step.
Even if you don't have the reference
file yet, you can just paste the context
here in the prompt and ask it to create
the reference file for that skill with
that context. Generally, you want to try
to keep the skill MD very clean and
focused on the process. Any additional
information should be in the reference
files. That's how your skill is going to
perform a lot better. And lastly, you
want to think about what you expect as
an output for each of the steps. So
something that I like to do and has made
a big impact on my productivity is when
you have human in the loop steps ask
cloth to always give you multiple
variations or options which you can
choose from instead of just one-off
outputs. So I usually say something like
that. It should give me five different
ways an infographic could visualize this
idea or concept. And then lastly you
want to think about rules for this
skill. Here you can basically predict
what could possibly go wrong when
executing this skill and write it down
as a rule. Now, this is also the section
that you will continuously update when
improving the skill. Two tips here in
the rule section is first of all to
double down on instructing it to use the
knowledge files as obligatory steps in
the process when needed. Otherwise, I I
notice it tends to skip over some. And
second, I usually double down on the
multiple variations with human in the
loop. And lastly, a really good thing to
include is progressive updates.
Basically, instruct the skill to be
automatically updated and improved when
using the skill so it becomes
self-learning. For example, every time I
define a clear thing not to do anymore
in this scale, update the rule section.
And what can be very powerful too is
instruct in the process that if a user
approved the final outcome to save that
as a good example so it learns and
builds more data around what good looks
like automatically. Now let me show you
a quick demo of how my infographic works
so you get a better idea of what you can
get out of this. So I'm in this case I'm
using the code tab here because uh with
API calls it can be a little bit easier.
Uh, so I can just trigger it with the
slash command. And this is already an
updated version from this initial prompt
that I gave it. First, it asked me what
content should I turn into an
infographic. So I'll just paste in a
part of my video where I talk about what
skills are. A later update I made from
this first prompt is to ask it first for
which platform it is to understand which
format it has to generate it in. So in
this case, LinkedIn and as you can see,
it uses these QA boxes because I
instructed it to do that. And then what
type of visual should it be?
Infographic. Then I later adjusted it
and iterated on it to get a checkbox
out. So I can actually start generating
multiple variations. But here it
suggests me what we should visualize.
This case I'll go with anatomy of a
skill. And then it suggests me ways to
visualize that concept. I can choose
what makes most sense and generate
those. I'll just do all of them.
Now again the first time I launched this
prompt, it wasn't this good yet. I had
to iterate three or four times, adding
extra rules, etc. So became an iterative
process. And it's really about that the
more you use it the better it becomes.
But these are quite powerful and really
follow my uh brands down and guidelines.
And you can see I added this box at the
end. If I click keep all finalize, it
will save it as the good output uh
examples. So it gets trained on what
good look looks like. Now it is
important uh how you instruct the model
to change things. Then an easy rule of
thumb you can keep in mind on improving
and updating is if it doesn't follow the
process correctly, ask it to make
changes to the skill MD. The key in the
skill MD is that it doesn't get polluted
with a lot of additional information. It
should mostly focus on the core process.
Now, if you need additional information,
you want to ask it to add a reference
file. Now, if it does something wrong,
not just for this specific task, but you
never want it to do, for example, I had
this with my infographic. I never want
the black background because the shadows
are not visible. Then you can ask it to
add a rule or update the knowledge file.
Now, if it struggles to use one of your
softwares, MCPs or tools, you can first
guide it manually to do the specific
action necessary and then ask it to
create an MCP reference doc on how to do
the task in the software. And you can
see that my first version is completely
different from my last version. Now,
lastly, once your skill is performing
well and you maybe want to share it on a
marketplace or maybe to a team member,
the easiest way is to ask Claude to give
you a zip file for that skill. You can
then just share that and someone else
can go into the settings, the
capabilities and upload the zip file.
You can also deploy a skill through
GitHub. I'll put a link in the
description below on how to do that.
Now, if you have multiple of these
skills, you maybe want to combine uh
different skills, maybe commands, adding
agents, specific connectors. You can
bundle them into a plug-in, which again
can be done by just telling Claw to
build you a plug-in. It will ask you for
all the skills, etc. that you want to
include and then you can add it to your
library and if you want to share it
again you can do it through a zip file
or by uploading it to github and if
you're a business and you have multiple
plugins across multiple departments you
can create an entire plug-in marketplace
which is a bundle of all your plugins
now you'd have to create this together
with cloth code and upload it to GitHub
in order to get a link again released a
full guide which I'll uh share in the
link in the description below now if you
want access to all of the skills plugins
uh me and my team are building out
including in graphic one. You can also
check out my AI uh accelerator, my AI
community where we list them all. We
also do weekly AI workshops where we
dive a lot deeper into these types of
tools. We have blueprints on how to
start your business, how to find your
first client. So, if that's potentially
interesting to you, uh you can check it
out in the link in the description.
Thank you so much for watching and if
you want to learn more about cloth
co-work uh you can check out the video
here above.